All right, here we go.
好的,開始囉
Ready...
準備好...
We did it!
我們辦到了
We finished the last tree!
我們砍倒最後一棵樹了
Man, I can't believe it.
天啊,我真是不敢相信
I guess anything is possible.
我想任何事都是有可能的吧
The two of us turned a whole forest into one field.
我們兩個將茂密的森林變成了田地
Yeah, it took us three years... no, more than that.
對呀,花了我們三年的時間... 不對,不只三年
If only all of this land belonged to us.
如果這片田地是我們的就好了
That's the disappointing part about being a slave.
這就是身為奴隸的悲哀
We really worked hard.
我們真的很拚命
It's almost time.
時候到了
Yeah... The other day, Pater told me
對呀,帕特前幾天對我說
that next year's yield from this reclaimed land
這片新開墾的田地下一批的收成
will be enough to buy our freedom.
將足以讓我們贖回自由
We'll even have a little extra left.
我們甚至會有一些剩餘
I see.
是喔
Einar, what are you going to do,
埃納爾,重獲自由之後
once you're free?
你打算做什麼?
I don't know.
我不知道
Even if I go back to my homeland, my family won't be there.
就算我回到故鄉,我的家人也不在了
Plus...
還有...
Is it about Arnheid?
阿奴納嗎?
Yeah, I feel bad.
對,我覺得很悲傷
If only Arnheid could be freed as well.
如果阿奴納也能重獲自由
Then I would be able to enjoy this moment more.
這個時刻會讓我感到更開心
The master has no intention of letting her go.
主人完全不想放她走
What about you, Thorfinn?
你呢,托爾芬?
Are you going back to Iceland?
你打算回冰島嗎?
Well, I guess.
應該是吧
Maybe...
或許...
What's up with that? You haven't decided on anything yet?
怎麼搞的?你還沒做出任何決定?
You haven't either.
你還不是一樣?
My goodness... It's strange, isn't it?
我的天...這種感覺很奇怪,對吧?
Our freedom is finally within reach, and this is our reaction.
我們終於要重獲自由了 結果我們竟然是這種反應
There is something I want to try.
我有句想說的話
Huh? What is it?
是喔?你想說什麼?
Oh, well...
這個嘛...
I don't have anything specific in mind yet.
我目前還沒有什麼明確的想法
Tell me what you think, Einar...
埃納爾,告訴我你的想法
Do you think
你覺得...
it's possible to rid this world
有辦法讓這個世界
of war and slavery?
不再有戰爭和奴隸嗎?
Well...
這個嘛...
It sounds like a dream.
聽起來像是一個夢
Oh, you've finally cut down the last tree!
噢,你們終於砍下最後一棵樹啦
Good work, you two.
幹得好,你們兩個
Master!
主人
Do you think you can grade this land in time for sowing season?
你們有辦法及時整地完成 趕上播種季節嗎?
Most likely, as long as we hurry.
只要我們加快速度的話,應該沒問題
Is that so.
是喔?
All right, then I will give you a little discount.
那好,我再給你們一些折扣
As soon as you finish sowing the seeds, you two will be free.
只要播種完成,你們就自由了
You deserve it, Thorfinn, Einar.
托爾芬、埃納爾,這是你們應得的
Oh, you don't seem too happy.
你們看起來似乎不太開心
Huh? Oh, no!
呃...不是啦!
Yes!
好耶
Right, Thorfinn? We finally did it!
對吧,托爾芬?我們終於辦到了
- Yeah!
-太棒了
Oh, sorry. Don't get too excited yet.
啊,抱歉,別高興得太早
What?
怎麼了?
You'll have to wait until I return to finalize the procedure.
你們得等我回來完成最後的手續
Oh, you're going somewhere?
您要出門嗎?
Yes. By the way, have you seen the old master?
沒錯,對了,你們見到了老主人嗎?
He hasn't come by here.
他沒有過來這裡
I see... Maybe he was out in the field after all.
是喔...他或許終於願意放下農事了
Well, you two will do.
好的,你們去忙吧
If you see the old master, tell him
如果見到了老主人,告訴他
that I will be heading to Jelling
我去耶林
in order to visit King Harald who is ill.
探望生病的哈羅德國王
But I should be back in time for the sowing season.
但我應該會趕在播種的季節回來
So finish grading the land by then.
到時要把地整好喔
Yes, sir!
是,主人
Have a safe trip!
祝您一路順風
Oh, I almost forgot...
啊,我差點忘了...
You two!
你們兩個...
Once you are freed, would you like to stay here
你們重獲自由之後,願意留下來
and work as farmhands?
當農場幫手嗎?
Hardworking people like you two are always welcome.
這裡永遠歡迎你們這種認真打拚的人
Well, try considering it.
考慮看看吧
WHAT DO WORKERS GAIN FROM ALL THEIR HARD WORK?
(工人辛苦付出之後 能獲得什麼?)
GOD HAS MADE EVERYTHING FITTING IN ITS TIME,
(上帝把一切都安排得切合時宜)
BUT HAS ALSO PLACED ETERNITY IN THEIR HEARTS,
(但也將永恒置於他們心中)
WITHOUT ENABLING THEM TO DISCOVER
(卻不讓他們察覺)
WHAT GOD HAS DONE
(上帝自始至終)
FROM BEGINNING TO END
(做了什麼事)
OLD TESTAMENT THE BOOK OF ECCLESIASTES 3:9,11
(舊約《傳道書》 第三章第九節、十一節)
All right!
好的
- Okay, let it down! - Yes, sir!
-好的,放下來 -遵命
Excuse me, Your Majesty.
不好意思,陛下
This ship will arrive at Jelling shortly.
這艘船即將抵達耶林
Please wake up, Your Majesty.
請起床,陛下
- Here I go! - Okay!
-我來囉 -好
- This one too, please. - Whoa!
-還有這個,麻煩了 -哇
- Ready? - Yeah!
-準備好了嗎? -好了
Your Majesty!
陛下
You were here, I see.
您在這裡喔
The horses will be ready soon. Please wait in the cabin.
馬匹就快準備好了 請在船艙裡稍等一下
I'm fine here.
我在這裡等就可以了
I haven't been home in a while.
我好一陣子沒回家了
I want to enjoy the breeze.
我想要享受一下微風
Your Majesty!
陛下
I am glad to see that you arrived home safely from England.
真高興見到您自英格蘭安全歸來
Yes.
嗯
Wulf, how is my brother, the king, doing?
沃爾夫,我的哥哥,國王還好嗎?
King Harald's condition is not very good.
哈羅德國王的狀況不太樂觀
His illness has worsened in the past month.
他的病情在上個月加重了
Now, it is difficult for him to even speak.
他現在甚至連說話都有困難
I see. How long does he have left?
了解,他還能活多久?
According to his physician,
他的醫生表示
the next few days will be the most critical stage.
接下來這幾天是關鍵
There!
那裡
Okay.
了解
Good work on paying him a visit as my representative.
謝謝你代表我去探視他,做得很好
Of course.
這是應該的
- Ouch! - I won again!
-好痛 -我又贏了
That ball game...
那個丟球遊戲...
When we were children,
當我們還小的時候
my brother was very skilled at that.
我哥哥很擅長那個遊戲
Once in a while, he would play with me.
他偶爾會跟我玩
Hit it, Harald!
要打中喔,哈羅德
All right. Keep your eye on the ball, Canute.
好喔,眼睛要緊盯著球喔,庫奴特
Within the royal court, there was hostility between those
宮中分別支持我們兩人 成為下一任國王的黨派
supporting either of us to become the next king.
互相仇視著對方
But my brother himself did not pay any regard to that.
但我哥哥本人對此毫不在意
Ready?
準備好了嗎?
There!
球來囉
- Your Highness! - Ragnar!
-殿下! -拉古納爾
I'm fine!
我沒事
Oh my!
我的天
See? He's tougher than you think.
看到了吧?他比你想像得還堅強
First of all, you're a bit overprotective.
你實在是太保護他了啦
- Be a little more-- - Amazing!
-給他一點... -太神了!
Jeez...
天啊
How impressive, Your Highness! Are you sure you're not hurt?
真是厲害,殿下 你確定你沒受傷嗎?
Yeah. Thank you, Ragnar.
對,謝謝你,拉古納爾
It's hard to move because I'm wearing so many layers.
因為穿太多層衣服了,讓我行動困難
And I'm hot! Can I take this off?
而且我好熱,可以脫掉嗎?
You mustn't!
當然不行
As a warrior, you must be prepared for anything.
身為戰士,你必須要做好一切準備
Are you listening, Your Highness?
你在聽嗎,殿下?
At any given moment...
在任何時刻...
He was a strong and kind person.
他都是一個既堅強又仁慈的人
My brother has helped me many times.
我哥哥幫助過我很多次
I must thank him.
我一定得感謝他
There!
接到了
Hey, kids! Play somewhere else.
孩子們,去別的地方玩
I'm sorry!
對不起
You throw it too hard!
你丟得太大力了
My goodness...
我的天
Children are so carefree...
孩子們還真是無憂無慮
What is the matter, Your Majesty?
您怎麼了,殿下?
It's nothing.
沒事
ENGLAND - DENMARK - NORMAY
(英格蘭,丹麥,挪威)
Sweyn's two sons
斯韋恩的兩個兒子
each inherited a dominion from their father.
各自從父親那裡繼承了一個領地
Denmark went to the elder brother, Harald.
丹麥給了哥哥哈羅德
England went to the younger brother, Canute.
英格蘭分給了弟弟庫奴特
The two were on good terms.
雙方關係友好
When Canute was going to conquer England,
當庫奴特準備佔領英格蘭時
his elder brother, Harald, lent him a fleet of warships
他的哥哥哈羅德將艦隊借給他
and actively showed his support for him.
主動對他表示支持
However...
但是...
shortly after Canute was enthroned as the king of England,
庫奴特成為英格蘭王不久之後
Harald fell ill.
哈羅德就病了
Harald had no heir.
哈羅德沒有子嗣
Canute, my brother!
庫奴特哥哥
So it was true that you were in Jelling.
你真的在耶林喔
Address me as king, Estrid.
叫我國王,艾絲特莉
I didn't expect your visit. What a nice surprise.
我沒想到你會來看我們 真是個意外的驚喜
It has been a while,
好久不見了
King Harald.
哈羅德國王
Harald, Canute has come to visit.
哈羅德,庫奴特來看你了
Can you recognize him?
你認得出他嗎?
It's fine. Don't wake him up.
沒關係,不要叫醒他
I will be here for a while.
我會在這裡待一段時間
We can talk when His Majesty is feeling better.
等到陛下舒服一些的時候,我們再聊
Canute...
庫奴特
King Harald, I am right here.
哈羅德國王,我就在這裡
Please get some rest.
請好好休息
There is no need to worry about the kingdom.
無需為國事擔憂
I was waiting for you.
我一直在等待著你
I will...
我...
I will hand over Denmark to you.
我會把丹麥交給你
Now, don't be absurd, King Harald.
你先別胡言亂語了,哈羅德國王
Please recover soon
請早日康復
and maybe we can play that ball game again.
或許我們能夠再玩一次丟球遊戲
You're really something else, Canute.
你著實不是等閒之輩,庫奴特
I don't know how you could feign innocence and tell such lies.
你竟然能夠睜眼說瞎話 我還真佩服你
Canute?
庫奴特?
You're visiting the very person you poisoned yourself?
你來探望你親手毒害的對象?
It's quite the farce.
還真是一場鬧劇
What in the world
你做得這麼絕
are you trying to accomplish by doing something like this?
到底為的是什麼?
Harald was fond of you.
哈羅德很喜歡你
Was there a need to kill him?
有必要殺了他嗎?
You two could have ruled this world together.
你們兩個大可一起統治這個世界
It is not for the peace of the kingdom.
這不是為了國家的和平
There is ambition dwelling in your heart.
這是你一直以來的野心
Ambition to become the sovereign over the North Sea.
你一心想成為北海的最高統治者
That is the curse.
這是個詛咒
The curse of the crown.
皇冠的詛咒
You cannot escape from it.
你逃不掉
You will wear two crowns,
你會戴上兩頂皇冠
one of Denmark and one of England,
分別是丹麥和英格蘭
and suffer twice as much as I did.
你所承受的痛苦會是我的兩倍
Canute!
庫奴特
What's wrong? You were zoned out.
發生了什麼事?你失神了
Are you ill as well?
你也病了嗎?
I'm fine.
我沒事
I just got a bit dizzy.
我只是有點頭暈
Get a bedchamber ready.
把寢宮準備好
King Canute is tired from his long voyage.
航行了這麼長的時間,庫奴特王累了
Yes, sir.
遵命
What is it?
怎麼了?
I have brought refreshments by order of Lady Estrid.
艾絲特莉夫人下令 要我準備一些茶水給您
Where is it from?
是哪裡來的?
Huh? What might you mean...
什麼?您這是什麼意思?
I don't need it. I'm not thirsty.
我不需要,我不渴
You fear poison
你害怕中毒
because you use poison yourself.
因為你會用毒
Isn't that right, Canute?
對吧,庫奴特?
Coming out in the middle of the day
在大白天裡出現
is very mischievous of you, King Sweyn.
你也真淘氣,斯韋恩王
If you can see me during the day too,
如果你在白天也看得到我
that means the curse is about to reach its climax.
那就表示詛咒的強度達到了最高點
He's talking to himself?
他在自言自語?
How long are you going to stay there?
妳打算在這裡待多久?
I don't need anything. Leave.
我什麼都不需要,妳走吧
Yes, sir!
遵命
The unification of the kingdom is a prerequisite for building a utopia.
王國的統一是打造烏托邦的先決條件
Having two kings will eventually lead to disaster.
有兩個國王終究會引發災難
It is necessary for King Harald to die.
哈羅德勢必得死
Well, well...
好說好說
You are starting to think like
你的思惟模式
a true king now, Canute.
開始像個真正的國王了,庫奴特
What are you laughing about?
你在笑什麼?
King Sweyn,
斯韋恩王
I used to hate you and wish for your demise.
我曾經很恨你,希望你死
But look at me now...
但看看現在的我
The only one I can be completely honest with
我唯一能說實話的對象...
...is you.
只有你
Let's stay good friends...
我們繼續做好朋友吧
as fellow cursed ones.
我們是受到詛咒的同路人
Harald, one more time!
哈羅德,再來一次
All right.
好的
- Ready, Canute? - Yes!
-準備好,庫奴特 -好
Harald.
哈羅德
We'll have a council of war. Come with me.
我們要開戰事會議,跟我來
Yes, Father.
好,父親
Sorry, Canute.
抱歉了,庫奴特
We'll continue this next time.
我們下次再繼續
Thank you, Harald.
謝謝,哈羅德
Become strong, Canute.
做個堅強的人,庫奴特
Stronger than me and Father.
強過我和父親
Understand?
懂嗎?
Yes.
好
All right, Your Highness!
好的,殿下
I will be your opponent next.
接下來換我當你的對手
What? You can play, Ragnar?
什麼?你也會玩,拉古納爾?
How rude!
真沒禮貌
I was once feared as
我曾經擁有過“河邊的古林博斯帝”
the "Lakeside Gullinbursti."
這個駭人的稱號
This is it, huh?
就是這樣,對吧?
How underwhelming.
還真平淡無奇
"King and Sword."
王和劍
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯:歐德慧